Guide to the Partners for Livable Communities collection, 1962-1994
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Partners for Livable Communities collection
1962-1994
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Partners for Livable Communities
C0021
27 linear feet (54 boxes)
This collection contains planning reports, studies, theses, dissertations, policy proposals, books, magazine articles, meeting minutes, and congressional hearings on various aspects of urban planning and community development dating mostly from the 1970s and 1980s. These materials were gathered by the Partners for Livable Communities in its effort to form a clearing house of information on urban and regional planning under the National Endowment for the Arts funded Architecture, Design and Planning Program.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Partners for Livable Communities in 2008.
Historical Information
Partners for Livable Communities (PLC) is a national, nonprofit organization working to restore and renew American communities by providing information, leadership and guidance that help communities help themselves. Founded by a consortium of the National Endowment of the Arts in 1977 under the title "Partners for Livable Places," the organization initially focused on design and culture as resources for livability.
During the 1980s the organization expanded its scope to address the economic concerns of communities and launched a number of programs, each focusing on a specific problem area of community development. The Economics of Amenity program secured PLC's place as a national resource dedicated to the economic value of using amenities for community development. It was soon followed by three other programs - Cities in Transition, The New Civics, and Celebrate the American Community - which approached community development in a more holistic manner that took open spaces and cultural centers into consideration as well as the impact of social and physical changes to the urban landscape.
During the 1990s the Shaping Growth in America program was launched to address issues of social inequity, children and families, minorities and the poor. The 1990s also brought a new name, "Partners for Livable Communities," and a redefinition of the Partners' Resource Center as the National Center for Community Action. PLC continues to work toward the growth and improvement of American communities to this day.
Scope and Content
This collection contains planning reports, studies, theses, dissertations, policy proposals, books, magazine articles, meeting minutes, and congressional hearings on various aspects of urban planning and community development dating mostly from the 1970s and 1980s. Much of the material deals with cities and regions in the United States, but the collection also features reports and studies on China and a number of European countries. The materials included in this collection were gathered by the Partners for Livability Community in its effort to form a clearing house of information on urban and regional planning under the NEA-funded Architecture, Design and Planning Program.
Series 1, Adaptive Reuse, contains materials on historic preservation and the reuse of old buildings and spaces for new purposes. It includes books outlining the cultural and economic benefits of adaptive reuse as well as case studies on the adaptive use of specific buildings, including industrial centers, loft apartments, museums, schools, historic railroad stations, and the Old St. Louis Post Office.
Series 2, Archaeology, includes a hand-full of materials on urban and industrial archaeology in California, the Northeast, and London.
Series 3, Central Business Districts, is the largest section of the PLC collection. It contains a number of planning reports, policy proposals, and books pertaining to the revitalization of central business districts and enterprise zones. The materials cover an array of U.S. cities including Los Angeles, San Diego, San Francisco, Baltimore, Bethesda, Washington, DC, Louisville, Dallas, Houston, Minneapolis, and Portland, Oregon. Some of the materials also deal with Canadian cities including Calgary, Edmonton, and Toronto as well as European cities including London, Berlin, and Amsterdam. Some specific items include a 1981 study on the revitalization of New York's 42nd St, a 1980 review of urban renewal in Amsterdam, a Bethesda streetscape plan from 1984, a comprehensive plan for the central city area of Racine, Wisconsin, proposals for retail development in Washington, D.C., and several studies on malls, farmers markets, and sidewalk cafes from the 1970s and 1980s.
Series 4, Cultural Facilities, contains materials on the municipal funding of public art and the development of community cultural facilities such as art centers, theaters, concert halls, and opera houses. The cities covered include Seattle, Rochester, Lowell, Knox, and Washington, D.C.
Series 5, Design, contains various technical, prescriptive, and theoretical materials on urban design, architecture, and landscape architecture. The subjects covered range from studies of classical Greek, Gothic, and twelfth-century Chinese architecture to surveys of contemporary British, German, Italian, and Swedish architecture to manuals on pedestrian design and articles on vandalism deterrence. The cities and regions covered include Berlin, Australia, Calgary, New Orleans, Brooklyn, rural Texas, and Concho, Arizona.
Series 6, Energy, contains numerous reports and studies on energy conservation planning as well as several congressional hearings on conservation policy. Most of the materials therein cover general issues (as opposed to case studies) including solar energy, bicycle transportation design, and making old buildings and historic districts energy efficient.
Series 7, Environment, contains plans and guidelines for environmental design and conservation in various regions including California, Delaware, northern Virginia, and Athens, Greece. The subjects covered include highway noise and beautification, rural land development, lake management, and water conservation.
Series 8, Handicap Accessibility, contains a small number of manuals on the incorporation of accessibility features into architecture and urban design.
Series 9, Open Spaces, Parks, and Recreation, consists mostly of plans and reports on the design and development of open spaces, parks, and cultural facilities. The subjects addressed include urban open spaces, parks, zoos, waterfront revitalization, and urban forestry in such cities as Dayton, Pittsburgh, Camden, Chattanooga, San Francisco, and Tampa.
Series 10, Public and Private Partnerships, includes reports and studies on the projects of various public and private partnerships aimed at developing the local economy, mitigating social inequity, and providing social services such as child care and urban renewal to the community. The partnerships examined in this series include the Bronx Land Reclamation Program, the Citibank Flatbush Project, the Missouri Neighborhood Assistance Program, and the Navy Broadway Complex Project.
Series 11, Tourism, contains reports and proposals pertaining to the promotion and development of tourism. The materials deal with such topics as the development of historic centers for tourism, tourist impact control, the 1980 and 1981 Travel Outlook Forum proceedings, the promotion of black material culture, and the "gritty city enhancement strategy," which aims to capitalize on the "gritty" ambience of old working-class neighborhoods and industrial centers as tourist attractions.
Series 12, Transportation, contains materials on the design and improvement of transportation infrastructure. Most of the studies cover general topics, but the series includes case studies of New York, New Orleans, Los Angeles, and the Netherlands. The topics covered include automobile restricted zones, center-city parking and parking lot design, transportation architecture, the economics of transportation restriction, traffic control design, railway and trolley transit, bicycle transportation and parking, and pedestrian relief areas.
Series 13, Urban Planning, is the largest section of the PLC collection after Series 3 (Central Business Districts). This series contains planning reports, policy statements, and congressional hearings on a wide range of urban planning and community development issues including economic development, land use, municipal tax policy, and suburban sprawl. Most of the materials deal with U.S. cities including Washington, D.C., Baltimore, Philadelphia, Madison, and Cincinatti, and such North American regions as Arizona, California, Texas, Oregon, New Jersey, Hawaii, Ontario, and British Columbia. However, it also contains studies on urban planning in China and a number of European countries including France, Italy, Spain, Poland, and the Netherlands. Within this series one will find numerous publications from the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development, several studies on Court House Plaza in Arlington, a 1972 report on Fairfax County, The President's National Urban Policy Report of 1980 and 1988, Reports of the European Campaign for Urban Renaissance, meeting minutes of the Council of Europe's 5th Symposium in 1977, and a dozen case studies from the "States and Urban Strategies" series.
Series 14, Oversize, contains oversize books on subjects that would otherwise be included in the following series: Central Business Districts, Cultural Facilities, Open Spaces, Parks and Recreation, and Urban Planning. It contains studies and planning proposals with large color photographs on San Diego, San Francisco, Baton Rouge, Chicago, and Providence, as well as Dublin, Ireland, and the Hague.
Arrangement
Organized into 14 series by subject with each series organized alphabetically by title.
Series 1: Adaptive Reuse, 1972-1981 (Boxes 1-2)
Series 2: Archaeology, 1967-1982 (Box 2)
Series 3: Central Business Districts, 1960-1989 (Boxes 2-13)
Series 4: Cultural Facilities, 1966-1989 (Boxes 13-16)
Series 5: Design, 1962-1989 (Boxes 17-23)
Series 6: Energy, 1975-1983 (Boxes 23-25)
Series 7: Environment, 1970-1989 (Boxes 25-28)
Series 8: Handicap Accessibility, 1975-1980 (Boxes 28-29)
Series 9: Open Spaces, Parks, and Recreation, 1971-1990 (Boxes 29-32)
Series 10: Public and Private Partnerships, 1976-1989 (Boxes 32-34)
Series 11: Tourism, 1965-1990 (Boxes 34-35)
Series 12: Transportation, 1962-1990 (Boxes 35-41)
Series 13: Urban Planning, 1956-1994 (Boxes 41-52)
Series 14: Oversize, 1967-1987 (Boxes 53-54)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
The George Mason University Special Collections and Archives has other materials on urban planning in the Planned Community Archives collection and on transportation planning in the, the, the John Roberts Hamburg Transportation Collection, and the James J. McDonnell Transportation Collection.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Partners for Livable Communities.
Subjects:
Buildings--Remodeling for other use--United States.; Central business districts--United States.; Energy Conservation--United States.; Open spaces--United States.; Tourism--United States.; Transportation--United States--Planning.
Contents List
- Series 1: Adaptive Reuse, 1972-1981; (1.5 boxes)
  This series contains materials on historic preservation and the reuse of old buildings and spaces for new purposes. It includes books outlining the cultural and economic benefits of adaptive reuse as well as studies detailing the adaptive use of specific buildings, including industrial centers, loft apartments, museums, schools, historic railroad stations, and the Old St. Louis Post Office.
  - Adaptive Reuse Feasibility Study and Proposal: Jessie Street Substation, 1977 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    John Weese, William Arno Werner, James M. Flack, et al.
  - Adaptive reuse gives life to old buildings, 1976 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Thomas J. Martin and Melvin A. Gamzon
  - Adaptive reuse of existing structures in Ohio, 1979 (Box 1, Volume 3)
    Judith B. Williams,
  - Adaptive use: development economics, process, and profiles, 1978 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Adaptive use: saving energy and money as well as historic buildings, 1974 (Box 1, Volume 5)
    Andy Leon Harney
  - Buildings reborn: new uses, old places, 1978 (Box 1, Volume 6)
    Barbaralee Diamonstein
  - Community harmony: the reuse of ordinary structures, 1980 (Box 1, Volume 7)
    Robert E. Mendelson
  - Conference on Recycling Old Buildings, 1974 (Box 1, Volume 8)
    Conference on Recycling Old Buildings (1974: Boston, Mass.)
  - Don't tear it down, 1979 (Box 1, Volume 9)
    Louis Joyner
  - Economic Benefits of Preserving Old Buildings, 1976 (Box 1, Volume 10)
  - Educational Facilities Laboratories booklet 1: A concerned citizen's guide to community school centers, 1978 (Box 1, Volume 11)
    Ellen Bussard
  - Educational Facilities Laboratories booklet 2: Planning community school centers, 1978 (Box 1, Volume 12)
  - Educational Facilities Laboratories booklet 3: Managing community school centers, 1978 (Box 1, Volume 13)
  - Educational Facilities Laboratories booklet 4: Facility issues in community school centers, 1978 (Box 1, Volume 14)
  - Educational Facilities Laboratories booklet 5: Using surplus school space for community school centers, 1978 (Box 1, Volume 15)
  - Educational Facilities Laboratories booklet 6: Resource book on community school centers, 1978 (Box 1, Volume 16)
  - Factory: a community development project, 1975 (Box 1, Volume 17)
    Albert A. Bogdan
  - Future from the past: the case for conservation and reuse of old buildings in industrial communities, 1977 (Box 1, Volume 18)
    Randolph Langenbach
  - Living cities: report of the Twentieth Century Fund Task Force on Urban Preservation Policies: background paper, 1985 (Box 1, Volume 19)
    David Listokin
  - Loft conversions: planning issues, problems, and prospects, 1981 (Box 1, Volume 20)
    Richard J. Roddewig,
  - Master plan and feasibility study, Massachusetts College of Art at the Boston Naval Shipyard, Charlestown. Draft, Part two, 1978 (Box 1, Volume 21)
    Massachusetts Bureau of Building Construction
  - Museums and adaptive use, 1980 (Box 1, Volume 22)
  - Old Post Office, St. Louis: the second generation, 1972 (Box 1, Volume 23)
    Stephen and Stephen Properties, Inc.
  - Recycling historic railroad stations: a citizen's manual, 1978 (Box 1, Volume 24)
    Anderson Notter Finegold, Inc.
  - Recycling historic railroad stations: a technical supplement to the citizen's manual, 1978 (Box 1, Volume 25)
  - Recycling public buildings, 1976 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    Judith N. Getzels
  - Regenerative components: the adaptive redevelopment of old industrial structures: draft report for comment, 1973 (Box 2, Volume 2)
    Institute for Architecture and Urban Studies
  - Rehabilitation: an alternative for historic industrial buildings, 1978 (Box 2, Volume 3)
    U.S. Heritage Conservation and Recreation Service
  - Rehabilitation: Fairmount Waterworks 1978: conservation and recreation in a national historic landmark, 1979 (Box 2, Volume 4)
  - Special place: creating a historic preservation/mixed use district in downtown Washington, D.C., 1988 (Box 2, Volume 5)
    Joint Project to Preserve Small Downtown Buildings
  - Urban recycling: rehab & remodeling of existing buildings offers a fast, profitable way into the in-town market, 1977 (Box 2, Volume 6)
- Series 2: Archaeology, 1967-1982; (9 volumes)
  This series includes a hand-full of materials on urban and industrial archaeology in California, the Northeast, London, and other regions.
  - Archaeological evaluation of primary and secondary impact areas of Central Contra Costa Sanitary District's stage 5B enlargements, 1976 (Box 2, Volume 7)
    David A. Fredrickson
  - Archaeology of London Wall: the third Sir Lionel Denny lecture of the Worshipful Company of Barbers, 1981 (Box 2, Volume 8)
    Brian Hobley
  - Background study archaeology: City of London Development Plan, 1978 (Box 2, Volume 9)
    E.G. Chandler, FRIBA
  - City of San Antonio, Alamo Plaza Paseo del Rio linkage project: prelimary case report, 1978 (Box 2, Volume 10)
  - Consideration of archeology and paleontology in the Federal-aid Highway Program, 1979 (Box 2, Volume 11)
  - Fort Stanwix National Monument: a master plan, 1967 (Box 2, Volume 12)
  - Industrial Archaeology in Troy, Waterford, Cohoes, Green Island, and Watervliet, 1973 (Box 2, Volume 13)
    John G. Waite and Diana S. Waite
  - Northeast Historical Archaeology, Vol. 4, Nos. 1 and 2, Spring 1975 (Box 2, Volume 14)
    Lee Hanson, editor
  - Object lessons in the city, 1982 (Box 2, Volume 15)
    Michael Rhodes
- Series 3: Central Business Districts, 1960-1989; (11.5 boxes)
  The largest section of the PLC collection, this series contains a number of planning reports, policy proposals, and books pertaining to the revitalization of central business districts and enterprise zones. The materials cover an array of cities in the U.S. including Los Angeles, San Diego, San Francisco, Baltimore, Bethesda, Washington, DC, Louisville, Dallas, Houston, Minneapolis, and Portland, Oregon. Some of the materials also deal with Canadian cities including Calgary, Edmonton, and Toronto as well as European cities including London, Berlin, and Amsterdam. Some specific items include a 1981 study on the revitalization of New York's 42nd St, a 1980 review of urban renewal in Amsterdam, a Bethesda streetscape plan from 1984, a comprehensive plan for the central city area of Racine, Wisconsin, proposals for retail development in Washington, D.C., and several studies on malls, farmers markets, and sidewalk cafes from the 1970s and 1980s.
  - 1982 downtown alternative plan (Box 2, Volume 16)
    Seattle, Washington Land Use and Transportation Project
  - 400 best ideas from downtown idea exchange, undated (Box 2, Volume 17)
    Downtown Research and Development Center
  - 42nd Street development project: a discussion document, 1981 (Box 2, Volume 18)
    New York State Development Corporation
  - 42nd Street development project: design guidelines, 1981 (Box 2, Volume 19)
  - Action program for the revitalization of downtown Hyannis, Barnstable, Massachusetts, 1977 (Box 2, Volume 20)
  - Alabama Avenue renaissance, 1982 (Box 2, Volume 21)
  - Alternative sources of municipal development capital: tax increment and industrial revenue bond financing for cities. V. 1, Description.., 1979 (Box 2, Volume 22)
    Floyd, Kennedy, and Associates
  - Alternative sources of municipal development capital: tax increment and industrial revenue bond financing for cities. V. 2, State-by..., 1979 (Box 2, Volume 23)
  - Amsterdam, a story of urban renewal, 1980 (Box 3, Volume 1)
    Koen de Pater,
  - Analysis of retail trade districts within selected British and American seaside resorts, 1969 (Box 3, Volume 2)
    Charles A. Stansfield,
  - Another of the city's distinctive neighborhoods, Soulard, 1981 (Box 3, Volume 3)
    Norbury Wayman,
  - Approved and adopted amendment to the sector plan for the Bethesda central business district, 1982 (Box 3, Volume 4)
  - Approved and adopted town center urban design plan: an amendment to the 1970 plan for Rockville, Maryland, 1979 (Box 3, Volume 5)
    Rockville, Maryland Department of Planning
  - Approved Bethesda streetscape plan, 1984 (Box 3, Volume 6)
  - Berlin: eine stadt auf der Suche nach der Zukunft = a city in search of its future, undated (Box 3, Volume 7)
    Harry Ristock,
  - Bethesda Metro Center: urban design statement, 1980 (Box 3, Volume 8)
  - Bethesda optional method applications: staff report, June, 1983 (Box 3, Volume 9)
  - Bethesda optional method projects reports: staff report: background information, April, 1983 (Box 3, Volume 10)
  - Bethesda streetscape plan: final recommendations for the core district, 1984 (Box 3, Volume 11)
  - Better life in towns, 1980 (Box 3, Volume 12)
    Yona Friedman
  - Better life in towns: European campaign for urban renaissance, ca. 1980 (Box 3, Volume 13)
  - Bloomsburg, downtown revitalization: a study and proposal, 1981 (Box 3, Volume 14)
    Thomas R. Deans Associates
  - Buffalo downtown data base: general report, 1977 (Box 3, Volume 15)
  - Build up Greater Cleveland for a better tomorrow, 1984 (Box 3, Volume 16)
  - Bunker Hill urban renewal project: history and program for completion, 1982 (Box 3, Volume 17)
  - Calculating benefits: what malls accomplish, undated (Box 4, Volume 1)
    Phyllis W. Haserot
  - Calgary "Plus 15" walkway system, 1985 (Box 4, Volume 2)
  - California Plaza, 1982 (Box 4, Volume 3)
  - Campus and community, 1980 (Box 4, Volume 4)
  - Capital budgeting and infrastructure in American cities: an initial assessment, 1983 (Box 4, Volume 5)
    National League of Cities
  - CDBG: a creative link to small-business development, ca. 1981 (Box 4, Volume 6)
    MATCH Institution
  - Central area plan review, principles, 1975 (Box 4, Volume 7)
    Toronto, Ontario Planning Board
  - Central city plan: a comprehensive master plan for the central city area, Racine, Wisconsin, 1975 (Box 4, Volume 8)
    Racine, Wisconsin Central City Committee
  - Centralized retail management: statement of program objectives, January 1986 (Box 4, Volume 9)
    International Downtown Association
  - Centre city concept plan, 1988 (Box 4, Volume 10)
  - Centre city San Diego: information packet, 1987 (Box 4, Volume 11)
  - Change and Growth in Central Boston, 1978 (Box 4, Volume 12)
    J. Thomas Black
  - Changing economic role of central cities, 1978 (Box 4, Volume 13)
  - Charleston Town Center, ca. 1984 (Box 4, Volume 14)
  - Cites, 1965 (Box 4, Volume 15)
  - Cities of New Jersey: primed for growth, 1986 (Box 4, Volume 16)
  - City and Town Centers: A Program for Growth: The Massachusetts Growth policy report, 1977 (Box 4, Volume 17)
  - City of Baltimore Annual Report, 1979 (Box 4, Volume 18)
    Wiliam Donald Schaefer
  - City of Rochester downtown development plan 1977-87: summary and recommendations, 1987 (Box 4, Volume 19)
    Rochester, N.Y. Department of Community Development
  - City of Tampa: Central business district development regulations, Chapter 43-B, 1982 (Box 4, Volume 20)
  - Civic Affairs: Street Prostitution in Our Cities, 1982 (Box 4, Volume 21)
    Bureau of Municipal Research, Toronto, Canada
  - Commercial and Industrial Condominiums, 1976 (Box 4, Volume 22)
    John C. Melaniphy, Jr.
  - Community development block grant program can be more effective in revitalizing the nation's cities, 1981 (Box 4, Volume 23)
    U.S. Comptroller General
  - Coordinated urban economic development: a case study analysis, 1978 (Box 5, Volume 1)
  - Coordinated urban economic development: a case study analysis: executive summary, 1978 (Box 5, Volume 2)
  - Dallas central business district streetscape, 1980 (Box 5, Volume 3)
    Myrick, Newman, Dahlberg & Partners
  - Dallas: this town may be an unlikely place for urban design sensitivity, but it's there, 1977 (Box 5, Volume 4)
    Nory Miller
  - Design and development program, downtown Washington, D.C., 1971 (Box 5, Volume 5)
    Okamoto/Liskamm, Inc.
  - Designated public views: on building downtown: 3A downtown pattern: A9 public views, 1974 (Box 5, Volume 6)
    George Baird
  - Designing the Successful Downtown, 1988 (Box 5, Volume 7)
    Cyril B. Paumier
  - Development guidebook: requirements for building in Baltimore City, 1981 (Box 5, Volume 8)
  - Developmental needs of small cities: a study required by Section 113 of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1977, 1979 (Box 5, Volume 9)
  - Downtown: a people place, 1988 (Box 5, Volume 10)
    Greater Washington Board of Trade
  - Downtown action planning process and program: executive summary, 1988 (Box 5, Volume 11)